<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preach'd at the funeral of the Right Honorable Sir Maurice Eustace Kt. late Lord Chancelor of Ireland at St. Patrick's Dublin the fifth day of July 1665 : together with a short account of his life and death / by W.S.B.D.</title>
            <author>Sheridan, William, 1636-1711.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1665</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 97 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 27 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A59759</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S3233</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R32139</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12334436</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12334436</idno>
            <idno type="VID">59733</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A59759)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 59733)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1027:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preach'd at the funeral of the Right Honorable Sir Maurice Eustace Kt. late Lord Chancelor of Ireland at St. Patrick's Dublin the fifth day of July 1665 : together with a short account of his life and death / by W.S.B.D.</title>
                  <author>Sheridan, William, 1636-1711.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 39, [8] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by John Crook ... and are to be sold by Sam. Dancer ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Dublin :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1665.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"The epistle dedicatory" signed: William Sheridan.</note>
                  <note>The brief biography in Latin: [8] p. at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Eustace, Maurice, --  Sir, ca. 1590-1661.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:59733:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:59733:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A SERMON Preach'd at the FUNERAL Of the RIGHT HONORABLE, Sir <hi>MA<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RICE E<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>STACE;</hi> Kt. Late Lord Chancelor OF IRELAND.</head>
            <p>At St. <hi>Patrick's Dublin</hi> the fifth day of <hi>July</hi> 1665.</p>
            <p>Together with a ſhort account of his Life and Death.</p>
            <p>By <hi>W. S.</hi> B. D. ſometimes Chaplain to his Lordſhip.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Memorare noviſſima &amp; in Aeternum non peccabis Seirach.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Dublin,</hi> Printed by <hi>John Crook</hi> Printer to the Kings Moſt Excellent Maieſty, and are to be ſold by <hi>Sam. Dancer</hi> in <hi>Caſtle-ſtreet.</hi> 1665.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:59733:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:59733:2"/>
            <head>TO THE Moſt Reverend FATHER in GOD, <hi>JAMES</hi> by Divine Providence, Lord Archbiſhop of <hi>Armagh.</hi> Primate, and Metropolitane of all <hi>Ireland,</hi> His Grace.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>May it pleaſe Your Grace,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S Your Graces Commands for publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of this enſuing Sermon, has put it beyond my power to conceal that from your Eye, which I thought very unwothy of your Ear; (though your Grace was pleas'd out of your great reſpect to my deceaſed Lord, to Honor it with Your preſence, when it was deliverd) ſo the ſmall opinion I have of its worth, and the no ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage which (I am ſure) it will add to my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, (being deſigned for a Country Auditory, where the Funeral was intended to be Selemnis'd) forces me to prefix Your Graces Name unto it: that I may not onely by its being own'd by Your Grace, be ſecur'd from the many cenſures which (I have cauſe to fear) ſhall paſs upon me; but alſo,
<pb facs="tcp:59733:3"/>that the thing it ſelf may be render'd the more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable, and carry the greater authority with it. I know (my Lord) Your Grace cannot be offended at this preſumption: becauſe it makes for the vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicating of of a perſon; who (I am certain) was no leſs Your Grace; freind, then Your Grace moſt juſtly deſerv'd: for that now your Grace has given the moſt convincing proofs of your Freindſhip, by Your endeavouring (ſeeing he cannot be his own compurgatour) to wipe of that dirt which ſome <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> out of malice and others for the ſupporting of their tottering intereſt bave caſt upon him to which if what <hi>I</hi> have here ſaid, may give but the leaſt aſſiſtance, I have (next unto your Graces pardon for this my confidence) all I deſire: becauſe I there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by diſcharge my duty unto my honored Lord, and have this oportunity offer'd, of publiſhing to the world, that I own my ſelf to be in the deepeſt ſenſe of duty, and gratitude imaginable.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>May it pleaſe Your Grace,</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Auguſt <hi>22. 1665.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Graces moſt obedient and moſt obliged Humble Servant,</hi> William Sheridan.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="biography">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:59733:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>2 KINGS 20.1. ISA. 38.1.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Set thy houſe in order, for thou ſhalt dye, and not live.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Ife and Death are the two Poles, on which all the Creatures rowl. Life is the firſt act moveable and continual of the living thing; and Death is the ceſſation of the ſame act: And there is ſuch a mutual ſucceſſive change of the one into the other, that the whole World has no other employment, but to conform it ſelf to their reſpective commands; and Man himſelf, though his ſoul be, as it were, a little god within him, and therefore might be thought not to need any other help for the preſervation of his being, than what flows from his own eſſence, yet lives not but by the groans of Creatures, and they are forc'd to ſacrifice their lives to preſerve his; yet at laſt, he findes, that the ſame day that lengthens his life in the morning, ſhortens it in the evening, and in the end, he is reduced to the common fate of Mortals. And God has decreed that this ſhould be ſo, becauſe he hath deſigned man for noble things, and ordained this life, onely for a paſſage into another; in which, rewards and puniſhments are irreverſibly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judged,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:59733:4"/>with reſpect to his actings: And being that Eternal happineſs is the ultimate end, which every man ſhould propound to himſelf, it ought to be his chief care, to perform all that is requiſite for the at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment thereof; and that is, to live and die well: The latter whereof, which does alſo implicitely com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend the former, cannot better be learnt, than from the example of King <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> to whom God ſends a Meſſage by the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> admoniſhing him of his death in the words of the Text; which does naturally divide it ſelf into theſe two parts, an Admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition, and a Reaſon: The Reaſon is firſt, in order of nature, <hi>Thou ſhalt dye, and not live;</hi> and the Admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion laſt, <hi>Set thy houſe in order.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, of the Reaſon, <hi>Thou ſhalt dye:</hi> Where, to omit ſpeaking of the changeable ſtate of our life, now ſick, and now well; now deliver'd out of one trouble, and now entring into another, which is the lot of all; but eſpecially of the godly, otherwiſe <hi>Hezekiah</hi> might have pleaded an exemption: I ſhall firſt enquire, what death is; yet not ſo, as to ſeek an exact definition of it, but to limit my Diſcourſe with theſe particulars:</p>
            <p>Firſt, its cauſe. Secondly, its effects. Thirdly its attendants: Which being diſcovered, will aſſiſt us to conceive more rightly of it.</p>
            <p>Firſt then, God is the cauſe of death, though he did not in the firſt order of nature appoint it to have a place in our kind; for notwithſtanding that the body of man was of corruptible matter, <hi>duſt of the earth;</hi> yet had he continued in his obedience, the Tree of life, as a ſupernatural remedy, perhaps alſo, as a Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the immediate communicating of life to man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde, had preſerv'd him from death; but in his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condary intention, in caſe man ſhould break his allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:59733:4"/>God ordained it; as by the words,<note place="margin">Gen. 2.17.</note> 
               <hi>In the day thou eatest thereof, thou ſhalt ſurely dye,</hi> does appear; for then came death by Gods appointment, in right, though not in event, upon <hi>Adam</hi> and his whole off ſpring: which is alſo confirm'd by S. <hi>Paul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 5.12.</note> 
               <hi>By one man ſin entred into the world, and death by ſin;</hi> ſo that man was the wilful bringer in of death on himſelf, by the permiſſion and appointment of God, who left him in the hands of his own choice, to live by obedience, or dye by ſin.</p>
            <p>Yet you are to take notice, that this death is not in us, as in other living creatures, a final deſtruction of the ſoul; nor is it fully underſtood by the names of <hi>ſleep,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Joh. 11.13. 1 Cor. 15.26.</note> and of <hi>enemy,</hi> given to it in ſcripture; for they are not of its common and univerſal nature; but are attributed unto it by way of ſimilitude; both in reſpect of our bodies which are in ſleep, as without ſenſe, and of the minde, which does after ſleep, more freely exerciſe its functions; as the minds of good men ſhall after the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection.</p>
            <p>It is call'd an <hi>enemy,</hi> for that it deſtroys the being of the Creature; and is therefore hateful, and hated, even where no ſin was, as appears by our Saviours Agony before his death; yet this <hi>enemy</hi> does Gods Saints a good turn, for that it brings them to <hi>everlaſting reſt:</hi> though that it does ſo, is not from its ſelf, but from the grace of Chriſt,<note place="margin">Heb. 2.14.</note> 
               <hi>who by his death has overcome death, and the Devil, who had the power of death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But that deſcription which the Wiſeman gives of it, does beſt expreſs its nature; where after he had ſet down the ſeveral incommodities and weakneſſes of old age, and coming to ſpeak of the end of our life, he ſaith, <hi>Then ſhall the duſt return to the earth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccle. 12.7.</note> 
               <hi>as it was, and the ſpirit ſhall return to God that gave it:</hi> Whence it appears, that death is the diſſolution of the body and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:59733:5"/>ſpirit, before joyn'd together in one <hi>hypoſtaſis,</hi> they both remaining ſtill the one in the matter of which it was made; and the other in reſerve with God from whom it came at firſt.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Its effects are theſe; firſt, It ends this life, and all the thoughts, actions and poſſibilities thereof: <hi>The dead know not any thing, neither have they any more a reward;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccl. 9.5, 6.</note> 
               <hi>their love, and their hatred, and their envy is now periſhed: neither have they any more a portion for ever in any thing that is done under the Sun:</hi> And this is to be underſtood of Supernatural and Religious, as well as of natural, and civil actions, and poſſibilities; for this life is the day; death brings <hi>the night, wherein no man can work:</hi>
               <note place="margin">John 12.</note> The wickedeſt man in the world, is in this life convertible;<note place="margin">Heb. 10.27.</note> but after death, <hi>there is no more hope,</hi> but <hi>a fearful looking for of judgement.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, it begins an unchangeable ſtate, both to the g dly, and to the wicked; for that to the one 'tis the end of all joy, the beginning of ſorrow, an ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting night, the gate of hell, the locking up of the door of comfort, and a ſad farewell for ever, and ever, with the joys of eternity.</p>
            <p>But to the other it is a ſtep to bleſſedneſs, the cloſe of mortality; and as <hi>Seneca</hi> ſaith, <hi>Tranſitus à labore ad refrigerium: a paſſage from labour to reſt;</hi> from expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to a reward; from a combat to a Crown; from death, to life; from faith, to knowledge, from a pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grimage to a Countrey; and, <hi>from the world, to a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: A gate of glory to the ſervant of God:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>S.</hi> Bernard. Greg. Naz. Auguſt. Ambr. de bono mort.</note> 
               <hi>A depoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this burthen of fleſh,</hi> which preſſeth down the free ſoul: <hi>And a journey to the city of God: The Midwife and birth-day of a better life; a reſt from labour, a death of miſery, and a burial of ſin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I cannot here, though I have a fair temptation offer'd
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:59733:5"/>me, inſiſt longer in confuting the <hi>dream</hi> of <hi>Purgatory</hi> (which the Romaniſts ſo ſtifly maintain, that they will ſooner renounce their ſhare of heaven, then quit their portion in that) then while I tell you, that it was firſt hatch'd by <hi>Plato</hi> in his <hi>Gorgias,</hi> or <hi>Phaedo,</hi> and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards adopted by the Council of <hi>Florence,</hi> about 1400 years after the death of Chriſt; during which time it ſuffer'd many Metamorphoſies and Tranſmutations, as it met with ſeveral Merchants: Diſcredited by the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, wherein ſome of their own ſide confeſs it has no ground; thruſt out of doors by the <hi>Greek Church,</hi> and ſo much diſcountenanc'd by them, that <hi>the Council of Baſil</hi> publiſhed an Apologie, directly diſallowing the Roman Doctrine of <hi>Purgatory;</hi> and how little they yet regard <hi>Pope Eugenius</hi> his preſſing them to receive it, is ſo notoriouſly known, that it needs no further declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and though it was entertained by ſome Ancients as a ſtranger, yet it was but upon trial of its good be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour, and was never made a free Denizon by the Latines, untill they found how profitable this Heatheniſh Brat was like to prove.</p>
            <p>Neither the ancient forms of Prayer for the dead, which were rather Commemorations or Thanksgivings, or a convoy to accompany the Saints into Heaven; or had reference to their ſecret Receptacles, which too many Fathers favour'd (but is diametrically oppos'd, to Purgatory) or to their publique acquittal at the day of judgement; or to the Conſummation of their hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs at the Reſurrection, or to the time of their tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>migration out of this life,<note place="margin">Origin. <hi>S.</hi> Ambr. <hi>S.</hi> Baſil. <hi>S.</hi> Hil. <hi>S.</hi> Hier. &amp; Lactan.</note> which it ſeems we do not abhor from, at our Anniverſary Feaſts of <hi>Chriſtmas, Eaſter,</hi> and the like, as if Chriſt were that day to be born, to ſuffer, or to riſe again, will warrant their <hi>Purgatory;</hi> no, nor the Purgatory fire in ſundry Fathers,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:59733:6"/>by which <hi>they</hi> meant no other, than the fire of Confla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gration, which ſhall conſume this world, through which they held,<note place="margin">Bibloh. l. <hi>5.</hi> annot. <hi>171.</hi>
               </note> as <hi>Sixtus Senenſis</hi> affirms from their own words, that all men both good and bad ſhould paſs, <hi>Chriſt Jeſus</hi> onely excepted.</p>
            <p>All this (I ſay) can no way prove their Purgatory, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially ſeeing the Scriptures know no other purgation for ſin,<note place="margin">John. 1. Heb. 1. Rev. 14.13. Heb. 9.27.</note> then the <hi>blood of Jeſus Christ;</hi> and calls none <hi>bleſſed, but thoſe that dye in the Lord;</hi> for, <hi>they reſt from their labours, and after death follows judgement;</hi> that is, the particular judgement of every <hi>individual,</hi> at the hour of his departure; and the general, of all at the <hi>laſt day.</hi> Where obſerve by the way, that <hi>it is appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for all men once to die;</hi> yet the hour is uncertain, and kept from us, that we might beware of ſecurity, and not defer our repentance to the laſt ſtage of our life, when happily the cuſtom of ſinning ſhall have ſo hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned us, that tis ten thouſand to one, whether we ſhall find place for repentance.</p>
            <p>I ſhall not now diſpute, whether death may be haſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, or prorogued: becauſe that if this were granted, it would argue a mutability in Gods unchangeable de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees; and yet if it were not, the Scriptures would ſeem contradictitious to themſelves; as, <hi>The blood thirſty man ſhall not live out half his days;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 55.23.</note> and this, of <hi>Adding fifteen years to Hezekiahs life.</hi> Onely this I ſhall make bold to offer by way of Solution of this difficulty, and reconciliation of this ſeeming diſſonancy of Scripture, That without all doubt, according to the courſe of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, many might live long who by intemperance and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godlineſs, <hi>cut off their days;</hi> and many, who are ſometimes in mercy taken away before their time from future evils.</p>
            <p>Yet this is not againſt Providence, becauſe that as it appoints the end, ſo likewiſe in that appointment it
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:59733:6"/>foreſees and includes the means leading thereunto; other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the ſame Objections would be in force againſt pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and the obedience of children to their Parents, on which condition, <hi>long life</hi> is promiſed.<note place="margin">Exod. 20.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Now it onely remains to enquire, Whether death be good or evil: Which cannot be eaſily reſolved, without ſome diſtinction of ſome perſons, or ſome reſpects; for Gods appointment is good, the puniſhment of ſin, is like ſin it ſelf, evil; an enemy is neither loved, nor lovely: Sleep is no evil thing, the entrance of life is deſireable, the determination of the life of grace is dreadful; we muſt therefore, before we can reſolve the queſtion, know of whom, and of whoſe death the demand is made; for the death of the Righteous is to be wiſhed for, witneſs <hi>Balaam;</hi> and the death of the wicked is wretched: And though <hi>Solomon</hi> ſeems to ſay abſolutely of all, <hi>That the day of death,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccle. 4.2.</note> 
               <hi>is better that of life;</hi> yet he muſt be underſtood to ſpeak there, as preſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing ſin, and the vanities, and miſeries that are annex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and conſequent thereunto; and ſo (indeed) a ſpeedy death is much better than a ſinful life; and that becauſe it is unfit to act that long, which is very ill done; and ſince life is often ſo deſperately uſed, it is expedient, not being good, that it be ſhort, that the ſhortneſs of the time, may render the evil of it leſs hurtful: But yet this does not abſolutely prove, that death is good, or better than life in all reſpects; for that an evil life may have, and without the greater grace, muſt have a worſe death.</p>
            <p>Death then in it ſelf, conſidering the ſtate of man fallen, unleſs we adde the quality of the death of the righteous, is evil; but conſidering man in a ſtate of grace, and as he is reſtor'd to the favour of God by Chriſt is good; for that it is an entrance into everlaſting joy.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:59733:7"/>
            <p>And thus have I done with the firſt part of the Text, or the Reaſon, <hi>Thou ſhalt dye, and not live.</hi> The ſecond part (which is the Admonition) follows, <hi>Set thy houſe in order:</hi> But before I ſpeak of this; give me leave to mind you of <hi>Iſaiahs</hi> ſevere manner of delivering this Meſſage, <hi>Thou ſhalt dye.</hi> Had he ſtopt there, <hi>Hezekiah</hi> might have comforted himſelf with finding out ſome allay; as, Thou ſhalt dye at laſt; or, thou ſhalt dye, and yet be miraculouſly reſtor'd again to life, as the man was by <hi>touching the bones of Eliſha;</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Kings 13.21.</note> but he cuts off all ſuch hopes by peremptorily adding, <hi>Thou ſhalt not live:</hi> Which clearly ſhews, that the Prophet told him this by ſpecial appointment, otherwiſe his prudence might be juſtly queſtioned; for that ſo abrupt a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration might ſo far deject him, that though his ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs were not in it ſelf mortal, yet it would take away all poſſibility of his recovery. And it likewiſe ſhews, that even good men themſelves, ſuch as <hi>Hezekiah</hi> was, can hardly be beaten from hopes of life: What we much deſire, we are loath to deſpair of; and you ſhall meet with very few, though never ſo deſperately ſick, but they ſtill reſerve hopes of life; <hi>Men are loath to take the ſentence of death,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 1.9.</note> as S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks; and there's ſcarcely any ſo old, but he hopes to live one year longer: Nay, Grace it ſelf doth not without ſome difficulty ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel nature; for S. <hi>Paul,</hi> though <hi>he deſires to be diſſolv'd, and to be with Chriſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 1.23.</note> yet ſindes himſelf in a <hi>ſtraight be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween two:</hi> But however, by occaſion of this ſpecial manner, not uſed to us in any particular ſickneſs, as it was to <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> it will not be amiſs for us, both for the croſſing of our fond hopes, and the convincing us of the uncertainty of our lives, to fancy that this Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage, <hi>Thou ſhalt dye, and not live,</hi> is now ſent to every one of us in particular; nay more, to conſider, that
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:59733:7"/>though we ſhould equal the life of <hi>Methuſalem;</hi> or the Ancients before the Flood, yet we ſhall die at laſt; and that if <hi>Xerxes,</hi> when he was muſtering his Army of more than two millions,<note place="margin">Herodot. Polymneia.</note> wept upon this reflection of his thoughts, that not one of them ſhould be alive a hundred years after: how much more cauſe have we to weep, and to be concern'd, for that every one of us who are now in this Church, ſhall not onely die with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in a hundred years, but a far ſhorter time; nay, for ought we know, before we get out of this place; and therefore this being ſeriouſly conſider'd, ought to make us more attentive to what we ſhall hear, in order to our preparations for death. If we had an Enemy that vow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to ſet upon us where ever he ſhould meet us, we would do our beſt to prepare our ſelves accordingly with weapons, and skill to encounter him:<note place="margin">Mortem op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tare malum timere pejus. <hi>Senec. Trag.</hi>
               </note> And being death is <hi>ſuch an enemy,</hi> nay, not onely a ſworn, but a mortal enemy too, it argues the greateſt madneſs imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, to be unprovided for its approach; and the baſeſt cowardize to run away from it.</p>
            <p>And truly, he that ſeriouſly conſiders, how many intercepting caſualties may hinder their preparing for death, who defer that work any longer than while it is <hi>call'd to day</hi> (not to mention that the very preſumption does much diſcredit the purpoſe) as the uncertainty of health, the ſuddeneſs of death, and the unfitneſs of the mind to learn to do well in the bodies weakneſs; and how horror and amazement, frenzy and diſtraction, may take away all capacities for, and poſſibilities of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance. I ſay, he that ſoberly and ſadly conſiders this, will eaſily grant, that then is the fitteſt time to make proviſions for death, when we are in health and proſperity, and while that is not ſaid, <hi>Thou ſhalt dye, and not live;</hi> which ſhall, or at leaſt may be ſaid to
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:59733:8"/>every one of us in particular at this inſtant. And therefore that we may be ſo prepar'd for death, as not to be diſmaid when <hi>this King of terror</hi> ſhall aſſault us, let us give heed to the Prophets advice, or admonition, which is the ſecond thing to be ſpoken to in the Text, <hi>Set thy houſe in order.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Text is word for word in the Original; Give charge or Commandment to thy houſe, which I account not to be onely the making of <hi>a Will</hi> (though that is a duty not to be omitted) but alſo the giving the <hi>laſt charge</hi> to his friends and ſervants, and the ordering and ſettling the affairs of his Kingdom; which <hi>Heze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiah</hi> was the more concern'd to do, becauſe he had no heir (<hi>Manaſſes</hi> being born three years after his recove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry) to whom the Crown might legally deſcend; and therefore it was by ſo much the more neceſſary for preventing of diviſions and quarrels in his Family and Kingdom after his death, to ſettle it upon the right Succeſſour.</p>
            <p>But it may ſeem ſomething ſtrange, that <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſhould give counſel about that in the firſt place, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as it may be thought to be the duty of a <hi>man of God,</hi> rather to adviſe him to ſettle his mind and conſcience: But the wonder will be removed, if you conſider theſe particulars:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> That beſides that <hi>duty</hi> which obliges a man to ſettle his eſtate; that others who have a juſt right thereunto, either <hi>by promiſe,</hi> or otherwiſe, may not be <hi>prejudic'd</hi> by his omiſſion, the very ſettling of <hi>tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral affairs</hi> in time of ſickneſs, is no ſmall part of preparing the mind and ſoul for God; for that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by all worldly thoughtfulneſs being laid aſide, he may the more vigorouſly betake himſelf to the making up of his accounts with God, and with leſs diſtraction
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:59733:8"/>bend his thoughts on his inward condition: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they that blame Miniſters in viſiting of the ſick, for adviſing them to make their wills, and to <hi>ſet their houſes in order</hi> (and ſuch mine own <hi>experience</hi> findes to be amongſt us) do but either diſcover <hi>weakneſs of judgement;</hi> or that which is yet <hi>worſe,</hi> a ſelfiſh deſign, that the eſtate of the <hi>ſick perſon,</hi> for want of ſuch timely diſpoſals, being divided <hi>into fractions,</hi> by the claims of <hi>ſeveral pretenders,</hi> they <hi>themſelves</hi> might hope to fiſh in troubled waters; and with <hi>the Dog</hi> in the Apologue, run away with the <hi>bone,</hi> while others are contending for it. But to return to our purpoſe.</p>
            <p>In the ſecond place you are to take notice, that it is not improbable, but that the Prophet knew, that <hi>Hezekiah</hi> was not unprovided for his ſoul. Or,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Perhaps, the Scripture gives us here onely the ſum, or chief ſcope of his advice: But whether this will ſatisfie or not, yet this is moſt certrin, that as our Saviour firſt bids, <hi>Seek the Kingdom of God;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 6.33</note> ſo it ought to be our chiefeſt care, for the attainment of that, to order our ſouls and conſciences aright; becauſe that imports more than all the world beſides, and every one is intereſted therein, though every one has not out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward eſtates and houſes to ſettle; and that the rather too, becauſe the <hi>Will</hi> cannot be made, until the <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience</hi> be rightly inform'd, for that ſome things may appear to be unjuſtly gotten, which cannot be bequeath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but muſt be reſtor'd: Wherefore if there be not ſome tolerable preparation of the <hi>Conſcience</hi> before, that muſt above all things be our firſt <hi>main care</hi> and buſineſs. And all that is requiſite to be done herein, may be reduc'd to one of theſe two intentions:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> To bring a man to dye in the <hi>favour</hi> of God: or,</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:59733:9"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> To give a man <hi>comfort and aſſurance:</hi> thereupon in the very conflict it ſelf, and that a man may dye in favour of God, he muſt firſt get it; and then ſecondly keep it.</p>
            <p>Firſt then, Gods favour is to be gotten; for all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind is fallen from it, and ſo are liable both to <hi>tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral</hi> and <hi>eternal</hi> death; and until the offence committed againſt God be removed, death is arm'd <hi>with ſin,</hi> as with a <hi>ſting;</hi> which being taken away, it has no more power to hurt. Hear then, that which is firſt taught, is how a ſinner may be juſtified, and reconcil'd to God, which for order ſake, I reduce to two heads: Firſt, <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance from dead works.</hi> And ſecondly, <hi>Faith towards God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 6.1.</note> both which are joyn'd together by the Apoſtle.</p>
            <p>I underſtand here by <hi>Repentance,</hi> that which has to do with ſin, both before, and in converſion: And it includes theſe four things;</p>
            <p>Firſt, Knowledge of ſin, not onely in general, that we are ſinners; but alſo in particular, how, and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in: Which knowledge is by <hi>the Law,</hi> becauſe that is <hi>the rule of our life,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 3.20.</note> by which we are to ſquare our particular actions; and <hi>the glaſs,</hi> which being look'd in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, clearly ſhews us our ſelves: And it is very advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagious in order to repentance, to examine our ſelves by this <hi>Rule,</hi> and to look into this <hi>glaſs,</hi> that if not all <hi>(for who can do ſo, ſeeing no man knoweth how oft he offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth)</hi> yet (at leaſt) we may diſcern as many of our ſins as we can.</p>
            <p>Secondly, as it includes the knowledge of our <hi>ſins,</hi> ſo likewiſe it includes our <hi>abhorrence</hi> and hatred of them, which muſt be accompanied with <hi>grief,</hi> and <hi>ſhame,</hi> and <hi>confuſion of face;</hi> for that we have offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſo bountiful a <hi>Father,</hi> and ſin'd againſt all the obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations of <hi>duty</hi> and <hi>gratitude</hi> imaginable. Not that this
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:59733:9"/>kind of <hi>ſorrow</hi> is in it ſelf ſimply neceſſary, or pleaſing unto God; for he onely requires our amendment, and delights not to <hi>afflict willingly,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lam. 3.34.</note> 
               <hi>nor to grieve the children of men,</hi> but becauſe there is ſuch a ſtrict coherence be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween this <hi>grief</hi> and amendment of <hi>life,</hi> that the one (as the needle, makes way for the thred) ſerves to uſher in the other; though if we conſider the conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of our nature, we have otherwiſe alſo juſt cauſe to be griev'd for our ſins; for that we are made thereby not onely deform'd in our ſelves, but alſo odious in Gods ſight, and deſerving of his juſt wrath, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected to the extreameſt ſeverities of the Divine Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance.</p>
            <p>And this kind of ſorrow is call'd <hi>Contrition</hi> and <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>punction;</hi> both which ſeem to be one and the ſame thing, in different forms of expreſſion: But if there be any difference between them, <hi>Contrition</hi> implies more than <hi>Compunction;</hi> for that by the one, is uſually meant the honour of <hi>puniſhment,</hi> and the ſting of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,</hi> which enſues upon the committal <hi>of ſin;</hi> and by the other is underſtood, <hi>ſorrow</hi> for the offence, without reſpect to the <hi>puniſhment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, This <hi>Repentance</hi> includes likewiſe confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our ſins,<note place="margin">Pſal. 32.51. Dan. 9.</note> that ſo we may not onely ſee what we have done, but what we have merited thereby, <hi>giving glory to God, before he cauſe darkneſs, and before our feet ſtumble on the dark mountains.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall not here ſtart that <hi>Queſtion</hi> ſo much contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted betwixt <hi>us</hi> and <hi>the Papiſts,</hi> Whether we be bound to confeſs our ſins to men. The <hi>Romaniſts</hi> themſelves acknowledge, that we are not bound to confeſs them <hi>before Baptiſm;</hi> and the truth is, we are not bound to confeſs them <hi>after,</hi> as to the obtaining of forgiveneſs from, and reconciliarion with God, eſpecially after
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:59733:10"/>ſuch a Sacramental, plenary, particular, inforc'd man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, under pain of damnation, and by virtue of Chriſts inſtitution, which they have in theſe laſt ages obtruded on the world; though indeed, as to the obtaining for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveneſs from men whom we have injured, and for the making of publique ſatisfaction to the Church, for a notorious ſcandal given, and ſometimes for obtaining counſel and direction in the anxieties and ſcruples of an erroneous Conſcience, and how to lead our lives in a penitential way of pleaſing God, it is very expedient to confeſs them unto men; but moſt eſpecially in the diſtreſſes of mind for ſins committed, when the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience gives a man <hi>caeca verbera,</hi> blind blows, like the vulture that continually gnaw'd upon the liver of <hi>Titius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vir. Aeneid.</note> that ſo the Miniſters unto whom God has com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted <hi>the Word of Reconciliation,</hi> might aſſure the Conſcience of pardon, and procure peace by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing a Sacerdotal Abſolution, <hi>a power which God neither gave to Angels nor Archangels:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chryſ. de Sacerdotio.</note> 
               <hi>But herein lies the wonder</hi> (ſaith a Father) <hi>that men inhabiting the earth, ſhould diſpenſe thoſe things which are in heaven, forgiveneſs of ſins.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, This <hi>Repentance</hi> muſt not ſtay here, but muſt carry us further, to beſeech the Lord for his mercy, and promiſe ſake, to forgive us our ſins: But becauſe this preſuppoſeth <hi>Faith,</hi> which is the next point, I ſhall reſerve it until I ſpeak of that; and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed <hi>faith</hi> and <hi>repentance</hi> are ſo link'd together, that I onely ſeparate them for Doctrines ſake: For never can true and compleat <hi>Repentance,</hi> be without <hi>Faith;</hi> nor true <hi>Faith</hi> be without <hi>Repentance.</hi> I confeſs that ſome degree of <hi>Repentance</hi> may be onely in a ſight of ſin, and ſorrow for it; and ſome kinde of <hi>Confeſſions,</hi> like that of <hi>Cain</hi> and <hi>Judas:</hi> But ſuch a <hi>Repentance</hi> is
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:59733:10"/>not with hatred of the <hi>ſin;</hi> but horror of the <hi>puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> And thus I come from ſpeaking of <hi>Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance,</hi> which is the firſt particular requiſite for obtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the favour of God, to ſpeak of <hi>Faith,</hi> which is the ſecond; wherein we muſt conſider, <hi>firſt,</hi> What it is: and <hi>ſecondly,</hi> how it may be obtain'd.</p>
            <p>Firſt, As touching what it is. You are to take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice, that the Scriptures ſometimes call by the name of Faith, that <hi>credit</hi> which we give to Gods Word; ſometimes <hi>power</hi> to work, or to have a miracle wrought; ſometimes <hi>trust</hi> in God, as in a ſtorm, <hi>Christ rebuking the fear of the Diſciples, askes, Where is your Faith;</hi> ſometimes <hi>perſwaſion</hi> that we ſhall receive ſomething from God, as when he bids us <hi>ask in faith, without wavering;</hi> and ſometimes as if it would exclude <hi>nothing, that the word ſignifies:</hi> But that <hi>Faith</hi> which reconciles to, and juſtifies before God, and which is here prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally meant, as it muſt be a <hi>Faith working by Charity,</hi> ſo it has for its <hi>next</hi> and <hi>immediate</hi> object, <hi>Chriſt</hi> the <hi>Redeemer;</hi> and for its <hi>final</hi> and <hi>ultimate,</hi> the <hi>whole Trinity:</hi> Yet it is confeſt, that this <hi>Faith</hi> preſuppoſes <hi>credit</hi> to be given to Gods Word, eſpecially to the Doctrine of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> that it is <hi>Divine</hi> and <hi>true,</hi> and it produces a <hi>perſwaſion</hi> of receiving the accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Gods promiſes upon performance of the <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions;</hi> but the <hi>former,</hi> not onely evi men; but the Devils themſelves may have; <hi>for they believe and trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble:</hi> And <hi>the latter,</hi> many times they that are <hi>reconcil'd</hi> to God have not, eſpecially in their firſt <hi>Converſions,</hi> or <hi>Relapſes</hi> into grievous ſins before their reſtauration; which happens, becauſe it is a <hi>conſequent</hi> of the <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer,</hi> and a fruit then onely preſent, when God vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafes to grant it: For as we ſee the Roſe tree bears flowers, but not in Winter, or it may be the firſt year
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:59733:11"/>it was planted, yet is apt to do ſo in convenient time; ſo this <hi>juſtifying Faith</hi> is apt to produce <hi>perſwaſion,</hi> though it does not always do ſo.</p>
            <p>Secondly, As to the obtaining of <hi>Faith:</hi> It is moſt certain, that we have not power of our ſelves to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve or acquire it; yet God has appointed ſome means in order to the attainment of it, which he uſually aſſiſts <hi>by his Spirit;</hi> and in the conſcientious practiſe whereof, he gives it in certain degrees: as,</p>
            <p>Firſt, By hearing the Word preach'd, he opens the underſtanding, and ſo illuminates it, that it may ſee what is deliver'd.</p>
            <p>Secondly, he convinces the judgement, that attends and conſiders well what is ſaid, and from the Majeſtie, Holineſs, Power and Conſonancy of the Doctrine, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes it is from God.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, When a man is thus convinc'd, he is not far from the <hi>Kingdom of heaven;</hi> for that he onely then lacks time to deliberate, Whether it be not moſt fit for him (all things being conſidered) to <hi>ſubmit</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, and <hi>obey</hi> this Doctrine: Whereupon being mov'd by <hi>Gods Spirit,</hi> he deſires <hi>Chriſt,</hi> which is the firſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree <hi>of faith</hi> in him; and prays the Lord for his ſake to have mercy on him: Which <hi>Faith</hi> thus gotten, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives new additions of growth and ſtrength, by the practiſe of pious exerciſes; as, the familiar hearing of Gods Word, Prayer, Meditation, and the frequent and holy uſe of the bleſſed Sacrament of the Lords Supper; and <hi>this Faith</hi> being added to the remorſe for our ſins, will <hi>be imputed to us for righteouſneſs, God thereby giving us Christ, and the life which he hath in him given to the world.</hi>
               <note place="margin">John 5.13.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And when the ſinner is thus <hi>reconcil'd</hi> to God, the great care muſt be, to ſecure his favour: For the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of which, he muſt,</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:59733:11"/>
            <p>Firſt, Abſtain from his former ſins; for God pardons ſinners, as Princes do Rebels, on condition they rebel no more: <hi>Go thy way</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>and ſin no more:</hi>
               <note place="margin">John 8.11.</note> 
               <hi>For as when the wicked turns from all his ſin which he hath committed, and does that which is lawful, and right, God will not remember his former wickedneſs: So when the righteous turneth away from his righteouſneſs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezek. 18.24</note> 
               <hi>and committeth iniquity, and doth according to all the abominations that the wicked man doth, all his righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs that he hath done, ſhall not be mention'd; but in his treſpaſs that he hath treſpaſſed, and in his ſin that he hath ſinned, in them ſhall he dye.</hi> Therefore we muſt not think it enough to have repented of our former ſins, unleſs we ſo repent as to forſake them; and ſo for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake them, as never to return to them again: But we muſt <hi>mortifie the fleſh by the Spirit, and not conſent un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the luſts thereof;</hi> that ſo we may evidence the reality of our repentance: Which while we do, though our infirmities will not ſuffer us to give a perfect and impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial obedience to the whole Law, yet this ſhall not be imputed unto us; for that we have <hi>a Law of liberty,</hi> whereby our actions are favourably interpreted, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the ſincerity of our endeavours, and the uprightneſs of our intentions, and not according to the rigour of Juſtice, and the meaſures of our weak performances: And while <hi>we walk in this light, ſo as our hearts condemn us not, we have communion with God, and the blood of his Son cleanſeth us from all ſin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly. We muſt walk circumſpectly, conſidering our actions, weighing our words, and <hi>watching over our thoughts,</hi> ere we give conſent unto them; <hi>ſetting our ſelves in Gods ſight continually,</hi> deſiring him to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect us, <hi>and to lay out the way before us,</hi> doing all the good we can, <hi>not conforming our ſelves to the world;
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:59733:12"/>but transforming our ſelves by the renewing of our minds, that we may prove,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 12.2.</note> 
               <hi>what is that good, that acceptable, and that perfect will of God.</hi> And though we may through the <hi>frailty</hi> of our <hi>nature,</hi> and the <hi>prevalency</hi> of a <hi>temptation,</hi> fall again after reconciliation into Gods <hi>disfavour,</hi> we muſt not altogether be diſheartned there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by; <hi>but renew our faith and repentance, being aſſur'd, that if while we were enemies, we were reconcil'd to God by the death of his Son,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 5.</note> 
               <hi>we ſhall much more be ſaved by his life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this done, the great care muſt be, that we die well: In order whereunto it is obſervable, that oftentimes it ſo falls out, that the ſtate of the perſon is not always diſcern'd by himſelf; and that though he is in favour with God, yet he is not aſſur'd thereof: Therefore it would be worth your inquiries to know, how the Conſcience may be aſcertain'd of Gods favour, preſuppoſing that we now ſpeak of ſuch as are in Chriſt, and have a right thereunto.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Then this is general, That whatſoever the cauſe of the doubt is, it is requiſite to evidence the truth of Repentance, and Faith, and to lead the <hi>party ſo affect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> to the renewed exerciſe <hi>of them,</hi> and to an earneſt invocation of God; whereto may be added the ſpecial uſe of the Miniſtry of Reconciliation, and the power of the keys, after the party is examin'd of the ſinceri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of his Repentance, and Faith, and purpoſe of new obedience. Beſides, ſpecial remedies are to be apply'd to ſpecial caſes; as if it ſhould happen, that the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience is perplex'd through its apprehenſions of the greatneſs, and number of its ſins; then this Conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is to be applied, that nothing is unpardonable, but final impenitence; and that the hainouſneſs and num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of ſins, is no bar to the favour of God, provided
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:59733:12"/>they be forſaken; as appears by the example of <hi>the Prodigal,</hi> and Chriſts own words, who <hi>came not to call the righteous, but ſinners;</hi> and that they are thoſe very men whom Chriſt came to call, and that there is a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial favour to ſuch, and <hi>joy in Heaven for their conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</hi> And laſtly, that oftentimes ſuch prove the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thieſt inſtruments of Gods glory; as <hi>Paul,</hi> who from a <hi>Perſecutor</hi> of the <hi>Faith,</hi> became a <hi>Propagator</hi> of, and a <hi>Martyr</hi> for the <hi>Faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. If the cauſe of doubt proceed from ſore and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual afflictions, which are oftentimes magnifi'd by fancy, or are but the products of paſſion; or melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly; it is to be intimated, that afflictions are not ſigns of Gods disfavour, but <hi>rather tokens of his love,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 12.12.</note> if they be born with patience, and that they give good advantage againſt death; for that they ſerve to make weary of life.</p>
            <p n="3">3. If the dying perſon (becauſe he findes himſelf aſſaulted with many blaſphemous temptations) doubts of his ſalvation, and concludes that God has given him over, and is not at hand to help him; he is to know, that temptations not conſented to, are not ſins, but croſſes; and that he is made no more guilty there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, than a good Subject is for being tempted by a Traytor to kill his Prince; or a chaſte wife by an Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terer, to defile her husbands bed; and that he is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to complain to God, and to beſeech him to rebuke the Devil; and that he would give him grace and ſtrength to reſiſt the temptation, and to endeavour to avoid all occaſions as much as he can.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Sometimes Gods children are ſo diſcourag'd by their relapſes into ſome groſs ſins after reconciliation, and through the ſenſe of their corruptions, and wants, that they not onely doubt, but pronounce of themſelves,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:59733:13"/>that God has caſt them away, and they charge them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with the ſin againſt the Holy Ghoſt: In this caſe they are to remember, that while they carry fleſh and blood about them, they muſt not think to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empted from its appendant inconveniences; and that Juſtification does not carry with it perfection, and free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom from all ſin; that many of Gods children, as <hi>Noah, David,</hi> and <hi>Peter,</hi> have committed grievous ſins, and yet have been forgiven; and that Chriſts Prayer, teaches the Apoſtles to pray for pardon; and therefore if they have fallen, they muſt <hi>confeſs their ſins, and Chriſt who is their Advocate is juſt and faithful, and ready to forgive them, and cleanſe them from all iniquity;</hi> and that being he will not cenſure them according to <hi>the Law</hi> of <hi>Bondage,</hi> but of <hi>Liberty,</hi> their defects ſhall not be examin'd in rigour, but pitied in mercy.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, Sometimes Gods children finde themſelves forſaken to ſuch a degree, that they are not onely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priv'd of the leaſt gleam of comfort, but their very devotion ſeems for a time to be extinguiſt, which ſo ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifies them, that they anticipate the very torments of Hell: In which caſe they are to take notice, that their trouble affords them matter of comfort; becauſe that their being perplext by his abſence, is from the ſupport of his Spirit, maintaining love in their hearts; which yet further appears, for that they would give the whole world <hi>to be reſtor'd again to the comforts of his ſalvation;</hi> and that though <hi>heavineſs endures for a night, yet joy cometh in the morning;</hi> for he will at length <hi>return, and quicken them,</hi> and therefore they muſt earneſtly entreat him ſo to do, and learn to live by <hi>faith,</hi> not <hi>feeling;</hi> and with <hi>Abraham,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 4.18.</note> 
               <hi>againſt hope, to believe in hope;</hi> remembring that Chriſt our Lord, was in this very con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, when <hi>he cry'd out, My God, my God;</hi> learning
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:59733:13"/>from his example in the greateſt deſertions, ſtill to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend upon him; and this being done, the moſt difficult part of fitting us for death is at an end; for that then the ſoul has great boldneſs with God, and can confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently cry out with <hi>old Hilarion, Egredere anima, egre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere quid pertimeſcis!</hi> and with S. <hi>Chryſostome, Give me to be aſſured of the joys of heaven, and then if thou wilt, kill me preſently; and I ſhall give thee thanks for thy pains; for that thereby thou ſendeſt me out of hand, into the poſſeſſion of thoſe good things.</hi> Here it may be ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable for a man to make his will, and to diſpoſe of his Eſtate; which I account not onely neceſſary, for that this may be a means (as I intimated before) of entailing peace on his Family, and of the better quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying of him, for the making his particular peace with God; but alſo, becauſe that the reviewing of his eſtate, (which is neceſſary in order to the ſettling of it) will happily give him occaſion to remember ſomewhat that he may have unjuſtly acquir'd, whether of things de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated to God, or uſurpt from men, and ſo be induc'd to make reſtitution of it, as he is bound by the <hi>Law:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lev. 5.15.</note> Where the <hi>Law,</hi> that <hi>a fift part ſhould be added to it,</hi> binds not (as I conceive) to that juſt proportion at this day, but onely enforces a compleat reſtitution; and indeed, ſince Gods bleſſing and favour is the beſt inheritance that can be left to children, and that none can hope for his bleſſing, either upon the robbery of him or man (not to mention the ſting of Conſcience that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſues thereupon) ſuch ill gotten goods are but a fooliſh and bad proviſion for poſterity:<note place="margin">Mich. 6.10.</note> 
               <hi>Are there yet the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of wickedneſs in the houſe of the wicked, and the ſcant meaſure that is abominable?</hi> Certainly, when God comes to viſit for theſe things, he will conſume both theſe ill gotten goods, and their neſt together; How
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:59733:14"/>much better were it for us to ſeparate them from what we have juſtly acquir'd, by reſtoring them to the right owners, than thus to run the certain hazard of Gods diſpleaſure? Here I cannot without injuſtice, omit praiſing our Anceſtors; for that they uſed in their laſt Wills, to make reſtitution of their Tythes negligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly paid, or forgotten: This ſin I am ſure is not yet left by ſome; but the amends making, nay the Tythes them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves are left out of their Teſtaments: It would be for their credit, to follow the example of that <hi>Honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Perſon,</hi> whoſe Funerals we now ſolemnize in <hi>this particular;</hi> and though they were not conſcious to themſelves of the leaſt defailance herein, yet they would do well to make mention of them in their <hi>Wills,</hi> for a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident to others. Neither can this conſideration, that a man by making ſuch reſtitutions, will happily expoſe his wife and children to miſery, and all the inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niencies of poverty, be a ſufficient plea againſt it; for that Gods friendſhip (which is entail'd upon the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drens children of them that fear him) is a far better proviſion than the <hi>Mammon of unrighteouſneſs: For he is the Father of the fatherleſs, and the defendor of the Widdow;</hi> and the committing of them to his care, is a kind of obligation upon him to provide for them; and therefore ſince his bleſſings make rich, and that many from ſmall or no beginnings, have been rais'd by him to great fortunes and preferment in the world, that ſhould fortifie them againſt ſuch ſolicitudes, and induce them to buſie their thoughts in ſtudying how to make them vertuous, and religious, and to leave it to God to make them rich, or at leaſt to provide <hi>food and raiment for them.</hi> And to this end, it is very neceſſary that they give them a charge touching the fear of God, as <hi>Moſes, Joſhua,</hi> and <hi>David,</hi> and others of the Saints of God have
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:59733:14"/>done. The laſt words (you know) of our dying friends make the deepeſt impreſſions, and are uſually beſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred; and this being the weightieſt point, on which the happineſs of our whole life depends, ought not to be forgotten.</p>
            <p>And thus having conducted the dying man (as well as I could) through all the ſtreights and duties neceſſary to be perform'd by him, in order to his dying in the favour of God, and to give him comfort and aſſurance thereupon in the very conflict it ſelf: I ſhall now before I come to any particular application, or to the perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of the ſaddeſt part of my task, preſcribe a few ſuch tame and gentle Cordials, as may onely help to keep up his ſpirits, and in ſome meaſure allay the pains of death in its more immediate, and nearer approaches; and that is, to mind him of the inſtances of Gods pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence and faithfulneſs in trouble, that he will not ſuffer any <hi>to be tempted above his ſtrength:</hi> And being there are many who ſuffer more from the fears of loſing their reaſon for want of reſt, and their patience through the extremity of pain, and ſo offend God; they muſt know, that the favour of God cannot be forfeited by the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtempers of the brain, or ſuch accidents as are occaſion'd by the diſeaſe; and if while the body is free from ſuch diſtempers, they do for prevention hereof, ſettle and confirm the Conſcience in the love of God, they may be ſure, that thoſe paſſions of idleneſs, raving, ſwear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or blaſphemy it ſelf, ſhall not be laid to their charge; becauſe that they are not of their own election: <hi>For as a Father pitieth his ſon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 103.</note> 
               <hi>ſo doth the Lord thoſe that fear him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As touching the pain of death (I am verily perſwaded) it is not neer ſo great as men apprehend; nor compara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to a fit of the Cholick, Gout, Stone, or Toothach
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:59733:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>it ſelf; and that for this reaſon, becauſe that in ſuch diſeaſes as are long and ſenſitive, ſtrength ſo much for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſakes the body before death fecks it, that a man cannot feel himſelf dye: Whereas in ſharper ſickneſſes it is otherwiſe; for that nature not being waſted, is able to make reſiſtance, and ſo renders its pain more pungent: But yet the ſhortneſs of them, makes them more ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portable; for that a man is cut off (as it were) at a blow, and ſurpriz'd by death before he has time to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider of it: However, though this be ſo, yet to encourage and fortifie the dying perſon againſt death, it will not be amiſs to have recourſe to the aſſiſtance of God in it, as that of the Pſalmiſt, <hi>Though I walk through the valley of death,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 23.</note> 
               <hi>yet will I fear no evil;</hi> to Chriſts Victory over death, who by his death hath taken away its ſting; to the aſſurance of glory which ſhall ſucceed; to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of Chriſt, and of his Saints and Angels; and laſtly, to oppoſe the very <hi>reſt from labour,</hi> which death ſhall ſhortly bring to the ſharpneſs of the preſent pain. And in the agony it ſelf, when the party is at the laſt gaſp, and the ſoul hovering in a trembling quandary, between its deſires of being freed from a Priſon, and its unwillingneſs to part with its old lodging: Then the great buſineſs muſt be to recollect the miſcarriages of his life paſt, that ſo he may rally his forces, to conſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate his graces, and to perfect his repentance; and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to minde that <hi>Chriſt ſits at the right hand of God to be his Advocate,</hi> he may confidently <hi>commend his ſpirit unto him, as into the hands of a merciful Creator:</hi> And when through the loſs of his ſpeech, or ſenſes, he is ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred uncapable of ſuch pious performances, then they that are about him are to ſupply his inability with earneſt prayer unto God, for the pardon of his ſins, for the grace of Chriſt, for the rebuking of Satan, and for the guard
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:59733:15"/>guard and tranſport of the holy Angels, and laſtly, when the ſoul is parted, as we pray, <hi>Thy will be done,</hi> ſo we muſt reſt ſatisfied therewith when it is done; comforting our ſelves with S. <hi>Pauls</hi> Doctrine concerning the Reſurrection, and the coming of Chriſt, <hi>And his bringing them that dye in him, with him again in glory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As touching the Funeral, though it may ſeem neither agreeable with my title, or purpoſe, to ſpeak any thing of it at this time; yet I muſt needs ſay, that as we are not on the one hand to bring in hired mourners, like ſo many Tiſiphones out of S. <hi>Ratricks</hi> Purgatory, to fill the Church with howlings, which has been deſervedly condemn'd by the primitive Biſhops, as diſagreeing with the Doctrine of the Reſurrection, and the life to come: So on the other hand we muſt take heed, that we run not into a contrary extreme with ſome Fanatical Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vators; and inſteed of a Chriſtian burial, bring in a dumb ſhew, having not ſo much as the leaſt expreſſion of a Chriſtian faith, or hope: Though it be true, that it was no prejudice to the bleſſed Martyrs, that their bodies were conſum'd to aſhes, or devoured by rave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous beaſts, or drown'd in the ſea; for <hi>the ſea ſhall give up her dead:</hi> And in this caſe that of the Poet holds true,</p>
            <q>Coelo tegitur qui non habet urnam.</q>
            <p>Yet in an ordinary way, there is a reſpect due to the bodies of the Saints deceaſed, as to the Temples of the Holy Ghoſt, the organs that he us'd to all good, waſh'd in the laver of Regeneration; whoſe members were the weapons of Righteouſneſs, which did partake of the body and blood of Chriſt, by which they <hi>glorified God in their bodies,</hi> and which being rais'd again in due time, ſhall <hi>be made conformable to the glorious body of Chriſt.</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:59733:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>Hence are thoſe offices we owe them, to wait upon their Herſe,<note place="margin">Luke 7.12.</note> as <hi>David</hi> upon <hi>Abner,</hi> and the Citizens upon the Widows Son, to inter them decently in the earth, our common Mother: And ſome reſpect is likewiſe to be had to a conſecrated place; for <hi>Joſeph</hi> deſir'd that his bones ſhould be buried in the Land of promiſe, where the Temple was to be erected; and if their ſtate re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire it,<note place="margin">Matth. 23.</note> to adorn their Sepulchres, to commend them in a Funeral Sermon,<note place="margin">2 Sam. 19.1.</note> or Oration, for the exciting others to their imitation; and howſoever the recital of ſuch godly Leſſons, Prayers and Exhortations, as may ſerve to moderate our grief for their loſs, confirm our hopes of the Reſurrection, admoniſh us of our own mortality, and to prepare us for our end, may be blam'd, <hi>yet with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out reaſon;</hi> for that by this, we not onely provide for their honour, but alſo ſatisfie our own mindes. This has been the practiſe of the Church of Chriſt in all ages, witneſs <hi>Dionyſius</hi> the Areopagite (or whoever elſe it was, certainly a moſt ancient Author) in his Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical Hierarchy;<note place="margin">Cap. 7.</note> where he ſets down their ſeveral Rites, their bringing the dead to the Church, their cof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fening of him, their ſalutations, their Hymns, their Prayers, and their Commemorations. He that will op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe his own fancy againſt reaſon, the authority and practiſe of the Church in all ages, I leave him to put on a coat which <hi>Solomon</hi> long ſince ſhap'd for him and his fellows, <hi>He that is wiſe in his own eyes, there is more hopes of a fool than of ſuch a man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have now finiſh'd my Text, and ſpent a great deal of time in telling you in a dull, flat, and unpoliſh'd manner, how you ſhould prepare your ſelves for death: And indeed the onely Apology for my ſelf, and ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction which I ſhall make to you for my offence herein, is to tell you, That death cannot be charm'd with a
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:59733:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſmooth tongue, nor kept off with a quaint expreſſion; and that it is the ſpecial duty of every one of you to believe, that what was here particularly ſaid to <hi>Heze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiah, Thou ſhalt dye, and not live,</hi> reaches alſo to you: And therefore my moſt earneſt ſute to you is, that you would for once be but true to your ſelves, and know, that in deſpight of all this Worlds Grandeur, and your own projects, you muſt die: Do but conſult your own bodies and ſenſes, and you will finde a decay in them; nay, if you will not be convinc'd by this, reflect upon thoſe cold Carkcaſſes, which now lie mouldring away in their hollow vaults under your feet; and ſince the eye of ſenſe moſt affects the heart, eſtabliſh your ſelves in this truth, by this ſaid Repreſentative; and behold here the Coffin of a perſon made up of all the Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butions of Nature, a Man, in whom concurr'd all that <hi>Pythagoras</hi> could think to beg of his god, to wit, Riches, and a firm conſtitution of body; and thence infer, that there is no exemption from the grave: For certainly if Greatneſs, if Learning, if Riches, if Parts, if Wiſdom, if Prudence, if Friends, if care of Servants, if At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendance of a Wife, if Skill of Phyſicians,<note place="margin">The thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving day for the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory over the Dutch was the day preceding the funeral. Hora. <hi>Palli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da mors ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quo pulſat pede paupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas regum<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> turres.</hi>
               </note> nay if the affections of moſt, and the prayers of many, could have ſecur'd him from death, our yeſterdays joy would not be ſo ſoon interrupted with this days ſorrow: But alas, no Grandeur can do it, for Death either findes all men equal, or makes them ſo. And therefore be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded <hi>to ſet your houſes in order,</hi> your inward, as well as your outward; your Conſciences, as well as your Eſtates; and conſider, that you who are yet breathing, are but hourly treading upon your own graves, lingring out a few uncertain minutes, and muſt neceſſarily fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low; and that God has given you this little reprieve, that you might prepare your ſelves for death; and ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:59733:17"/>you are repriev'd onely during pleaſure, and know not how ſoon you may be call'd upon to execution, do not put off this ſo neceſſary work one moment; but even now, betake your ſelves to the making of your Wills, to the perfecting of your accompts, and take no reſt, until ye get your pardon ſeal'd; for remember, that God himſelf,<note place="margin">S. <hi>Ambro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </note> though he has promis'd pardon to the penitent, has not promis'd to ſtay one day for his repentance: For it <hi>is to day, this</hi> very day, <hi>if you will hear his voyce,</hi> that you muſt <hi>not harden your hearts, or elſe he has ſworn in his wrath, that ye ſhall never enter into his reſt.</hi> And if there be any of thoſe here pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, who becauſe they have beauty, and youth ſpark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in their veins, ſo far deſpiſe death, that they will ſeek it in the midſt of dangers, as if they ſcorn'd it ſhould come unſent for, and leave it to be fear'd onely by the aged and the ſickly; let me aſſure them, that they will finde a vaſt diſproportion between dying in a fit of a Rodomontado, and dying in cold blood, and that death is not the ſame thing in the hands of a man, as it is in the hand of God; and that a <hi>Lord have mercy on me</hi> an hour or two before we dye, is not probably a ſufficient preparation for it: No, no, it is the Work of works to dye well, that is, actively and chearfully to reſign life; and they that have ſpent their whole time therein, have found it little enough.</p>
            <p>But though your neceſſities, and the importance of this ſubject tempts me to inſiſt more particularly on it, yet the intereſt which the Honorable Perſon (whoſe Obſequies we now ſolemnize) has in this our meeting, forbids that, and commands me to beg you attention to as ſad a ſtory, which muſt needs beget a treble paſſion of ſorrow, joy, and emulation in all that hear it: Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, for our loſs in him; joy, for his gain in our loſs; and
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:59733:17"/>emulation, in all of his virtues. But before I come to this, I muſt needs tell you, that my thoughts have for ſome time wav'd me to and fro, and that I am yet in ſome ſuſpence, whether I ſhould ſpeak or not; for that I account it no eaſie matter, to be Moderator of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments that are for Speech or Silence; for that on the one ſide, whilſt the Miniſter is pouring oyl on the face of the dead, to make it ſhine, he does but too often caſt dirt in his own, and withal, may be very prejudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial to the living; for that many (whoſe lives ſpeak nothing for them) will be apt to draw the example into conſequence, and ſo hope to hire a Hackney Fune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Sermon, to carry them to Heaven when they dye. And on the other hand, <hi>though common graves have no Inſcription, yet marble tombs are not without ſome Epitaph:</hi> And Heroical examples ſhould not go without a trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet; but being my place forbids me ſilence, all that I ſhall premiſe, either for your information, or for ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curing my ſelf againſt the various cenſures and opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which are like to paſs upon me in this great Audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory, is to minde you, That we are not come hither, with intentions to imitate the Egyptian Prieſts; who upon recounting the good and bad deeds of their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed at their Funerals, were wont to deny them bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial, if they found their vices to exceed their virtues; no! Chriſtianity teaches us more charity, and therefore we are not now oblig'd to diſcloſe the frailties or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfections of the dead, whatever they were; no! we are rather to deal with'um, as the Painter did with <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gonus,</hi> who had but one eye, he drew his Picture <hi>imagine luſcâ,</hi> half fac'd, and ſo cover'd the deformity from the beholders ſight; and to bury them in everlaſting oblivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as the Iſraelites did their <hi>exerements without the camp;</hi> and that the rather, becauſe (I may ſpeak it with ſome
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:59733:18"/>confidence) God has ſo buried them, that they ſhall never riſe up in judgement againſt him; but whatever was in him Juſt and Honourable, Vertuous and Noble, Chriſtian and Religious, Pious and Charitable, we are bound to remember, becauſe we are bound to imitate.</p>
            <p>I ſhall not take upon me to play the Herald, to rip up his pedigree, or blazen his Coat of Arms, but onely ſo far, as may encreaſe your eſteem of him: for when Nobility and Vertue grow out of the ſame ſtock, they command reſpect, by adding mutual luſtre to each other.</p>
            <p>He was deſcended from an Ancient and Noble Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, many of which were no leſs eminent for their parts and employments, than they were ſignal for their Loyalty, which juſtly advanc'd them to the higheſt commands in this Kingdom. And though afterward by the common viciſſitude of all Sublunary things, this ancient Family fell into decay, ſo that they might put the Moon upon their ſhooes, as the old Romans did upon their gates, to ſhew the volubility of all worldly enjoyments; yet it has now not onely receiv'd a new life; but alſo a new addition of honor and renown from that Worthy Perſon, who made it his buſineſs to derive his honour more from his own Excellencies, than from the merits and Grandeur of his Anceſtors.</p>
            <p>He was admitted a Member of the <hi>Colledge</hi> adjoyning to this City, in the year 1610. where (under the tuition of that Learned and Reverend Prelate, <hi>Anthony Martin Lord Biſhop of Meath</hi>) after he had taken the degree of Batchelour in Arts, he was choſen Fellow; and having paſt the reſt of the courſe of his ſtudies, and perform'd all his Exerciſes with that general ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe, which is uſually the reward of hard ſtudy, and pregnant wit, he commenc'd Maſter, and was choſen
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:59733:18"/>Hebrew Lecturer; and by his accurate knowledge in that Language (a thing rare in men of his Countrey) and his great care in inſtructing his pupils, he made early diſcoveries of his future preferment. But after he had ſpent full nine years <hi>there,</hi> in the good eſteem and love of his acquaintance, having by ſtudying of Divinity firſt learnt to manage his own Conſcience (as if Providence had ſo deſign'd it on purpoſe) that he might the better know how to keep his Majeſties. In the year, 1619. he was (by the perſwaſion of his friends) remov'd to <hi>Lincolns Inn;</hi> where he made it his buſineſs not to learn the Modes and Vices of the place, but to qualifie himſelf for the ſervice of his King and Countrey: And <hi>there</hi> he has left ſuch ſurviving Monuments of his great parts, and greater induſtry; that it may be diſputed, Whether the <hi>Society</hi> was to <hi>him,</hi> or <hi>he</hi> to the <hi>Society</hi> the greater ornament. But no ſooner did his own abilities, and the neceſſities of his Countrey call him from <hi>thence,</hi> to engage in the publique practiſe of the Laws, but the Lord Chancellour <hi>Loftus,</hi> a perſon, who beſides his many other extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry endowments, was very well able to judg of men, took him into his particular favour, and not onely commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted all his private concerns unto his management, but very much relied on his advice and opinion in the moſt intricate matters of Chancery: And having thereby given ſufficient proof of his parts, his great faithfulneſs and ſound judgment repreſented <hi>him</hi> ſoon after as a very fit perſon to be of His <hi>Majeſties</hi> Learned Council: Whereupon being made Serjeant by his late <hi>Majeſtie of ever bleſſed and glorious memory,</hi> that did but publiſh to the world his deſerts and fitneſs for greater employs; and therefore a Parliament b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing call'd by the <hi>Lord of Strafford, a perſon of great excellency, but far greater
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:59733:19"/>misfortunes,</hi> he was by the unanimous conſent, and to the general ſatisfaction of the whole Houſe, plac'd in the Chair; where he gave ſuch proofs of his ſo great abilities and judgement, of his ſo great Prudence and Conduct, and manag'd that affair with ſo much advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage to His Majeſties intereſt, and the ſtate of things then, that the <hi>Lord Lieutenant</hi> did not onely confer Knighthood upon him, but the whole <hi>Houſe</hi> by their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral recommendatory Letters to <hi>His Majeſtie</hi> in his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half, declar'd their approbations of him, as well as their obligations to him.</p>
            <p>But when Pride and Ambition began to contend with Loyalty and Obedience, and Rebellion had uſurpt Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, and turn'd Order and Government into Anarchy and Confuſion; then this Mirrour of Loyalty was no leſs ſerviceable to <hi>His Majeſtie,</hi> by his aſſiſting the now <hi>Lord Lieutenant</hi> with his private counſel, than he was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in his publick capacity. Then it was, that the <hi>Duke of Ormond</hi> was perfectly acquainted with the deep judgement, and great integrity of Sr. <hi>Maurice Eustace;</hi> and that Sir <hi>Maurice Euſtace</hi> was confirm'd in his belief of the <hi>Duke of Ormonds</hi> undaunted courage, and unal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terable reſolution of running all hazards for <hi>His Majeſties interest;</hi> and ſo by their mutual knowledge of one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers faithfulneſs, they eſpous'd each others concern, and His Majeſties in both. But when Rebellion began to get the maſtery, and <hi>His Majeſties intereſt</hi> was going down the wind, and the Sword forc'd out of the hands of His <hi>Lieutenant,</hi> and Treaſon it ſelf became meritori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, <hi>this Honourable Perſon</hi> ſo far ſcorn'd to be tempted to any thing that was baſe or unworthy, that to the extreme hazard of his life, to the utter ruine of his eſtate and fortunes, and ſeven years impriſonment in <hi>Chester</hi> added to all this, he ſtill perſever'd in his adhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:59733:19"/>to the Royal intereſt. And when His <hi>Majeſties</hi> affairs were accompanied with ſo many evil circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, that the ſucceſs of the Traytors made them ſo ſecure in their Uſurpation, that they ſet the Priſon gates wide open, and permitted <hi>him, Anno</hi> 1655. to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pair to this his native Countrey again, his wiſdom added to his faithfulneſs, begot ſuch jealouſies and fearful ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions in the Uuſurpers, that they could not think themſelves ſecure, until they ſecur'd <hi>him</hi> the ſecond time in this Town: Then they rifle his ſtudy, and would fain make his Loyalty to his Prince, and his Vicegerent, many of whoſe Letters he had then in his hands, and which were the ſignal inſtances of <hi>his innocency,</hi> the moſt aggravating evidences of his <hi>guilt:</hi> But God, that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd this Honourable Perſon for greater ſervices, <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver'd him</hi> this time alſo, <hi>out of the paw of the Lion,</hi> and preſerv'd him for the happieſt of times, that of His Majeſties Reſtauration.</p>
            <p>And here ſecure your ſelves (if you can) from being ſurpriz'd with an Extaſie of admiration, and behold and learn the quinteſſence of all Loyalty from this Worthy Patriot; nay, ſuch a Loyalty, as is rarely found, drain'd from all its baſer mixtures of particular intereſt, or ſelfiſh deſign; for whereas a man ſhould have thought, that a perſon ſo deeply ſuffering, and highly meriting, ſhould have been impatient, and greedy of reward; <hi>he</hi> on the contrary, acquieſces in the general good of the happy revolution, and accounts himſelf more than re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded, for that he lives to ſee his lawful Prince reſtor'd to his undoubted Rights. And when <hi>His Majeſtie</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires him to be <hi>Lord Chancellour,</hi> and one of the <hi>Lords Juſtices</hi> of this <hi>unfortunate Kingdom,</hi> with an Augmen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of ſallery; <hi>he</hi> not onely refus'd it modeſtly, and in complement, as ſome men are wont to do thoſe things
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:59733:20"/>which they moſt defire, that they might be preſt with the greater earneſtneſs on them, but uſes his utmoſt power to avoid it: And at laſt being convinc'd, that His <hi>Majeſties</hi> ſervice ſhould be highly advanc'd by his ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance, <hi>he</hi> embraces it with this thankful acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgement, and unfeigned proteſtation, which I hear give you in his own words.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Moſt Gracious Soveraign, Your Majeſtie has this day committed to my charge, the greateſt truſt in Your Majeſties three Kingdoms, by delivering unto me the cuſtody of Your Majeſties Great-Seal, which is the grand ſecurity of the lives and eſtates of Your Majeſties good people there; and which is more, if more can be, Your Majeſtie has thereby constituted me to be your own Repreſentive, to perſonate Your Self in Your Majeſties moſt high and honorable Court of Chancery in</hi> Ireland; <hi>to diſtribute Your own Conſcience, by moderating the rigour of Your juſtice, according to the rules of equity and good conſcience, among Your good people there: And good God!</hi> Who is ſufficient for theſe things! <hi>as the great Doctor of the Gentiles ſaid in another caſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Moſt glorious Sir, I muſt needs confeſs my unworthineſs of ſo great an honour, as well as my inability to make any ſuitable acknowledgement: But this I promiſe, that no man ſhall diſcharge that great truſt with more faithfulneſs then I ſhall; I will by Gods help, preſerve clean hands, no bribes ſhall ſtick to my fingers, no poor man ſhall be wearied out of his right by long attendance; and my chief endeavours ſhall be, to preſerve a clear conſcience towards God and man. In a word, to uſe that Royal expreſſion in</hi> Magnâ Chartâ <hi>confirm'd</hi> by Your Majeſtie <hi>in this preſent Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as it was in thirty Parliaments before,</hi> Nulli Nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bimus, nulli vendemus, nulli deferemus jus. <hi>And this I do promiſe to Your Majestie, in the preſence of God,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:59733:20"/>and of Your Majeſties moſt Honourable Privy Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And truly, he was ſo punctual in performing hereof that I dare challenge any, except thoſe ſordid and way<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſpirits, who will never learn to ſpeak well of the dead, to lay the leaſt breach of this to his charge; or to find the leaſt injuſtice or partiality in any of his proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, unleſs they will be ſo diſingenuous, as to accuſe him of ſome ſlowneſs in diſpatch of buſineſs towards the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter end of his days, which were rather the effects of his age, and indiſpoſition, and the fear of doing injuſtice oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſioned thereby, than the products of his choice.</p>
            <p>I ſhould too much injure his memory, if I ſhould paſs by in ſilence his great zeal, and cordial affection for the Church of <hi>England;</hi> whoſe both Doctrine and Diſcipline he ſo impartially weighed, that his being a zealous Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor of the true, ancient, Catholick and Apoſtolick faith (in no Church in the whole world ſo purely taught as in that) was not ſo much due to his Education, as it was to his election: And how conſtant he was in the Publick Worſhip of God, after this manner which our Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries on the one hand <hi>call Hereſie,</hi> and on the other <hi>Popery,</hi> moſt of you are no leſs eye-witneſſes of, than I am of his Family and private Devotions.</p>
            <p>Hitherto you have heard but very little (and that too, very diſadvantagiouſly related) of the morning and noon of his days; but that is yet behind, which moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns you to know, as well for your imitation as his praiſe: For ſince it is the evening that crowns the day, and that all the miſcarriages and defects of a vitious life are expung'd by a pious and penitent death, it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns you to have a more particular account of his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour therein. And therefore, no ſooner did God by a fit of the Palſie ſend him this Meſſage, as to <hi>Hezekiah,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:59733:21"/>Thou ſhalt dye, and not live;</hi> but immediately calling for his Chaplain, he reſigns himſelf up to God with the prayers of the Church; and by his pious re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flexions and heavenly ejaculations, proceeding from a ſoul repleat with fervour and devotion, he ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently prov'd, that he was better able to inſtruct and prepare his Chaplain for death, than his Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lain was to prepare him. And then finding his diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to encreaſe, and little hopes of having <hi>fifteen years added to his days;</hi> after this tolerable preparation of his conſcience, he betakes himſelf to the <hi>ſetting of his houſe in order;</hi> that his thoughts being wholly wean'd from the world, he might with the more advantage ſpend the remainder of his time in ſtating of his accompts with God. And here I can never ſufficiently admire and adore the unſpeakable goodneſs of God towards him, that although he died of ſuch a diſeaſe, in which men are cut off (as it were) at a blow, yet he had ſo per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect uſe of his reaſon, memory and ſpeech, though he was ſometimes defective in the laſt, that there is not one word in his whole will, which is not of his own dictating, or at leaſt of his approbation; for he very well knew, how advantagious it was to his Family, to make his Teſtament ſo clear, and perſpicuous, as that it may draw no Law Suits after it. And in the reviewing of his eſtate, he bequeaths not the leaſt part of it to the Church, but leaves all his Impropriations, amounting at leaſt to ſix or ſeven hundred pounds a year, as a pious Legacy unto it, and twenty pound a year towards main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining of an Hebrew Lecturer in the Colledge; <hi>by which he has for ever conſign'd this great truth to all worthy Perſonages, That as they love God, at the ſame rate they are to make proviſion for his Prieſts.</hi> And now after he made ſuch diſpoſals of his eſtate, as are juſt
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:59733:21"/>and honourable, pious and charitable, and that can never be queſtion'd, unleſs by a ſtrange ſort of people, whone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver think any thing well done, that tends not to the gratifying of their own covetous pretenſions: He gives his Phiſitians a diſmiſs, and ſummons all his forces to aſſiſt him in perfecting of his repentance, and in trim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, and ſnuffing of his Lamp, that it might burn the brighter, and caſt the greater luſtre, he leaves no ſlut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh corner unſwept in his Soul; nor parlies with any one beloved ſin, but thruſts them all out of doors, to make room for Chriſt, whom he confeſs'd they had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſo often juſtled out of his heart. And with no leſs abhorrence of himſelf, then hatred of his ſin; while the juſtice of God is ready to overwhelm him with diſpair; he ſupports himſelf with the conſideration of his former mercies. Then it was, that he approved himſelf not onely a good Textuary, but a good Divine: for that as often as his memory, or they who aſſiſted him in that charitable Office furniſht him with Scriptures ſuitable to his condition; his own experience enabled him to make the application: Now he confeſſes that it is no time to diſſemble with God; nor to cheat his own Soul, And therefore endeavours by his redoubling of his ſorrow for his ſin, and by the fervency of his Prayers to evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence the truth of both. And being alarm'd with the brisker approaches of death, and finding a ſenſible de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay in his Spirit after he had taken as long a time, as his condition would admit of, to prepare himſelf, and acknowledged with <hi>fear and trembling, that ſeeing Chriſt ſent his Diſciples to prepare a room for the celebration of the Paſſeover: How much more need of preparation did he ſtand in for receiving of Chriſt himſelf.</hi> And having added unto this an humble and penitent confeſſion of his ſins, he received the Holy Sacrament of the Lords Supper ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:59733:22"/>with ſome eſpecial freinds, with a reverence and devotion becoming ſo Sacred a Myſtery,<note place="margin">His own La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Mrs. <hi>Ford</hi> Sir <hi>Richard Kenedy,</hi> the Proveſt of the Colledg and others.</note> and being overtaken with a ſhort nod, he checkt himſelf, <hi>with a what? Could'ſt thou not watch with me one hour? The Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit is willing, but the fleſh is weake, O Lord pardon my in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now with old <hi>Simeon</hi> having taken Chriſt into his arms, he finds a calme in his conſcience, which with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doubt was an antepaſt of that <hi>Everlaſting reſt</hi> which he now enjoys. He takes a ſoleme farewell of all his freinds; and addreſſing himſelf more particularly to one of them, gives him this laſt Charge, and evidence of his perſevering Loyalty, <hi>fear God, ſerve your King, and lead a good life.</hi> And then after he had more than once committed his Soul both actively, and chearfully into the hands of God, with a <hi>ſweet Jeſus receive my Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and Come Lord Jeſus, come quickely:</hi> His ſpeech felt a ſtop forſome time, but neither our prayers nor his un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, for a little after the bi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d of Paradiſe being ready to fly out of his Cage gives us notice of his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture, by ſinging with a tunable voyce, ſome few verſes of the 25 <hi>Pſalm:</hi> And then his ſpeech quite for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaking him, his hand, and his eys were faithfull inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preters of his inward devotion.</p>
            <p>And thus have we brought this honorable Perſon to the borders of Eternity, and have ſaid no more of him then what was requiſite for your inſtruction: And to the end that what was excellent in him, and therefore imitable, may have the deeper, and freſher impreſſion on your memories. I ſhall once more tell you in a word, that he was a learned Scholler, a profound Lawyer, a wiſe States-man, a juſt Man, a true Freind, a thankfull Perſon where he was obliged, a munificent Benefactor to the Church, a loyal Subject to his King, a faithfull Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:59733:22"/>to the houſe of <hi>Ormond,</hi> a zealous profeſſour, and maintainer of the Doctrine and diſcipline of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> abhorring <hi>Popery</hi> on the one hand, and <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nataciſm</hi> on the other: and that whatever the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar failings of his life were. (I am confident) he dyed a Penitent, and a good Chriſtian in the Communion of that Church, in which he accounted it his greateſt hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyneſs to have had his education.</p>
            <p>And now if any hereafter, ſhall out of envy go about to uncover his nakedneſs, or to revive the memory of any of his infirmities, or for want of charity unto me look upon what I have now ſaid, as the products of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, or aſſentation; I ſhall onely make this defence for my ſelf, that I profeſs in the preſence of God, whom if I ſpeak the truth, I deſire may be my juſtifier, but if a lye my puniſher: that I have given you here, as true and impartial a relation of his end, as if I were now to make my laſt account to God; and as this can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but ſatisfie all thoſe, who are able to diſtinguiſh co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours, and to diſcern truth from falſhood: So I ſhall take no other pains for the ſatisfaction of thoſe peeviſh and perverſe diſpoſitions, who are reſolv'd before hand, not to be ſatisfied with any thing; then to tell them <hi>that I account it a ſmall thing to be judg'd by men, for that I muſt ſtand or fall to my own Maſter,</hi> and that it much more concerns them, to amend what they find defective in themſelves, then thus uncharitably to cenſure others, that ſo they may not one<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y deſerve to be well ſpoken of here, but at laſt, be admitted into that everlaſting reſt, from labours, which now (as we have good cauſe to hope) that honorable perſon (whoſe Funerals we have Solemnis'd) is in Poſſeſſion of.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div xml:lang="lat" type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:59733:23"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:59733:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Oratio Funebris HABITA In Aula Collegii <hi>S. S.</hi> &amp; Individuae TRI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NITATIS, Coram Academia, Iudici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, &amp; clero inter celebrandas ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>equias Inſigniſſimi viri <hi>MA<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RITII E<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>STACE</hi> EQUITIS AURATI, <hi>Hiberniae</hi> Cancellarii Ejuſdemque olim Regni Juſtitiarii, 5<hi rend="sup">o.</hi> 
               <hi>Julij.</hi> 1665.</p>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Requens hoc dicendi genus (Auditores) Solitaque haec perorandi conſuetudo, &amp; innocua haec cum Manibus colloquia, unà cum ipſis creverunt ſaeculis, tempori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que coaeva ſunt; adeo ut ne ipſa qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem mors (inter Heroas velim) ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis familiaris ſit, quam funerum ſolen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitas: id enim privilegii ſemper habuerunt viri Illuſtrio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res ut facundè expirarent, &amp; quas hauſerunt animas inter Oratores ponerent, eas (in exitu ſaltem) ex Harmonia com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitas probaturi, faeliciori, in hoc, fato functi, quod eo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:59733:24"/>vel exequia inter delicias numerarentur. Abſit itaque hodiernae Pompae invidia, neque is aſſentandi libidine laſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vire exiſtimetur, qui defunctorum geſta modeſtè recitat; hoc enim non tam artis quam pietatis eſt officium, &amp; inter le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viores Rhetoras habendus est, qui ſtudet cineribus adulari, vel tumulorum umbras captitare; at neque creſcenti nepo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum famae haec conſecramus encomia, ne Vicariè quidem ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blandientes, ſed ut novos ediſcant potius quam antiquos vindicent honores, Egregiae quippe animi dotes nulli haereditario jure devoluuntur, nec in aſſe virtus eſt, Indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidua haec Aeternitati comes per inexplicabilis gyri ludens miracula nec incipit nec deſinit, ſed ultrà omnes limitum terminos luxurians, inſe uſque &amp; uſque redit, ſuumque ſibi complementum eſt.</p>
            <p>Quam imparem ſubeunt provinciam, quantumque in mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis argumentis laborant ingenia; veſtrum Auditores teſtor dolorem: Oratorem itaque praeſenti quam apprimè utilem negotio nacti eſtis &amp; Gravitati conſonum, ignaris etenim nulli melius vel obſtupeſcunt vel admirantur: neque tamen ulla <hi>Euſtacii</hi> gloriae vis infertur quod mutuari laudes non poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit; nec ei demptum quid exindè reperitur, quod in tanto Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nere Rhetoricantur inepti, vel muti hactenus eloquuntur. Cum enim (ut in Cancellario noſtro) eò animi Majeſtas evecta ſit; ut ultrà artes ſedem poſuerit; quolibet a praecone ebuccina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, in publicas delabitur curas parilemque omnibus tam ſcribendi materiam quam licentiam ſuggerit: licet enim in tantis Magnitudinis Anguſtijs loqui ridiculum videretur; tacere tamen nefas eſſet, ne a poſteris in Illius fati comme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moratione ſilentes, non tam rudes, quam ingrati habere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur.</p>
            <p>Conveniſtis itaque non unius viri interitum, ſed noſtri orbis infortunium ploraturi: in <hi>Mauritio</hi> enim quicquid
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:59733:24"/>grande vel magnificum ſonat; quicquid nominis honeſtas vel claritudo pollicetur; quicquid denique vel vulgus ſolet, vel fama poſſit fingere, interierunt omnia, &amp; in communi hâc urnâ tumulantur: tituli nempè illi mortalitatis hami &amp; illecebrae; crebri tumeſcenteſque plebis plauſus, muſicae iſtae magnorum procellae, a populari aura, Syrene novâ blandiûſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que crudelt excitatae, imo &amp; honores illi, quos veros men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timur, ferè omnes in illius Epitaphio laſſati dormiunt: qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi ideo ſolummodo grandeſcerent homines ut Auguſtiùs pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rirent nihilque inter humana magnum &amp; memorabile, prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter monumenta duraturum ſit, tanquam lemniſcatis ideo fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis, vittatiſque honoribus ideo induerentur nobiles, ut ſolen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niores tantum fiant victimae, &amp; opima magis morti ſpolia exhibituri ſint.</p>
            <p>At ſua nihilominus unguenta virtus habet, ſuuſque ſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metipſi bonus quiſque Marcelianus eſt; interque aromata ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat Pyramidum capſulis longè dulciora, &amp; Mauſolaea con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequitur multo certiora, quam quibus vel a Corintho vel a Memphide poſſit donari: &amp; hâc immortalitate <hi>Euſtacius</hi> no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter pluſquam felix eſt, ſic adhuc eſt ſuperſtes, cumque ipſa emorientur ſepulchra ſibi futurus Rogus eſt, ultraque oblivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onis invidiam vivet, Illiuſque memoria ſemper recens, efflo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſcenſque ſemper, vel cum ipſa temporis ſenectute juveneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cet.</p>
            <p>Sed quia nulla ſit fortunae amplitudo quantumuis maxima quae ſua non habuit incrementa (aliqua enim in immenſis methodus eſt) pace veſtra Auditores liceat retroſpicere, &amp; ſi de cunis &amp; <hi>Euſtacio</hi> ſimul loqui non ſit piaculum, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitemus illum aliquando infantem, aliquando natum, (ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que enim par eſt ut inter tot virtutes, viri obliviſcamur) huic itaque Regno natalitias debet, familiâ oriundus anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quâ aeque ac nobili, ſed quae inter tot tantaſque Illuſtrium
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:59733:25"/>imagines nuſquam ſuperbit magis, magiſue ſibi, quam in <hi>Mauricio</hi> ſuo gratulatur; quanquam etenim Domus illa per tot lustra claruerit, ut dubitari poſſit, an Antiquiorem ipſe Solnaturae primogenitus, ortum jactaverit; infinito tamen huic computo addidit <hi>Mauricius</hi> ſplendorem, novoſque ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perinduxit radios, quibus ipſa Claritas perſpicua magis &amp; illustris reddebatur.</p>
            <p>Iamque (Auditores) indulgete pauliſper pietati, mihique copiam facite, ut inter tot <hi>Euſtacij</hi> inſignia, &amp; unum Matri noſirae Tholum ſuſpendam: In illo, Academia noſtra &amp; Viduatur &amp; orba eſt, filiumque Virumque unà amiſerat; hic cunas habuit, eademque ubera quae Vos alunt, illa a quibus <hi>Uſherus</hi> lacteas coeli Vias, imo ipſos Coelos Exuxerat, <hi>Euſtacio</hi> maturitatem contulerant; nec erat de Collegij Vulgo, at Juvenis ille <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndiquaque nobilis, inter Sodalitij proceres adſcitus, Socius fuit, &amp; in hoc mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarum Regno <hi>par</hi> habebatur; Neque enim Eccleſia tantum ſed &amp; curia <hi>Feliciori</hi> hujus loci genio ſuos debet Prima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes: At non aliquorum inſtar graviter infanteſcentium, maternos inter amplexus conſenuit, ſed ut aetate, ita &amp; curâ provectior ad altiora ſe accinxerat, totumque ſe cui natus eſt Reipublicae impenderat; primaque optimae indolis ſub <hi>Straffordio</hi> (tum rerum tum hominum aeſtimatore opti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo) ſpecimina edidit; In Cujus Parliamento Prolocuto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris Vice fungebatur, &amp; tantam ſibi inde conciliavit glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am ut nihil tunc dierum praeter Crumenam deerat quin Cancellarius audiret. At illi ſoles nimis eheu candidi e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant; illi dies faelices nimium nimiumque <hi>Regii</hi> erant quam qui vulgo placerent; tunc fuimus Troes, tunc Trinobantias &amp; ingens rerum gloria ſtetit: at in ipſis (credite mihi) Imperijs aliquid foemineum eſt, &amp; gravis illa Reipublicae facies ad ſpeculum componitur, ubi ſe Fortuna intuetur, ſi bique eodem momenti turbine placet, diſplicetque, brevique
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:59733:25"/>novitatis ſtatim inoleſcentis affecta taedio, mutatque, corri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitque, perque omnes laſciva metamorphoſes tranſcurrit, nec eâdem vultus Serenitate ſemper effulget, ſed inornatis ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quando ſparſiſque capillis videtur ſquallere: &amp; ea hujus regni tunc facies erat; nec Comis tantùm ſed &amp; capite ſploliabatur, impiaque fortuna ſuis devecta rotis, Caroli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que quadrigâ incedens, tria vertigine regna rapuit, in qua ruina cecidit <hi>Euſtacius;</hi> Neque enim hic stetiſſe Robur animi ſed imbecillitatem denotaſſet talemque vel <hi>Alexander</hi> ambiret caſum, elabente mundo; ſic perijſſe non tam clades erat quam pietas, nec infortunium ſed obſequij munus, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lapſis enim Regioe domus fundamentis <hi>Stantia non pote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant Tecta Probare Deos:</hi> Hujus Excidij pars erat <hi>Mau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricius,</hi> qui licet non totus occubuerit, mortuus tamen vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xit, &amp; quamvis tumuli beneficio non redimebatur, pro buſto carcerem ſubivit, Vivuſque tumulabatur, &amp; catenis, mortis compedibus durioribus ſuo ſe devinxerat Carolo: Inter has ille procellas immotus manſit, Ruinae tamen publicae minime expers, ſed infracti erat animi, &amp; tanquam ſcopulus in mari Britannico natabat, Inſulae<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> inſtar flu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>itantis, ipſe ſibi in Diluvio erat Continens, in tantis ille mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus nihil de animi conſtantia remiſerat, ſed malignio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem ferendo fortunam correxit; Nec cum Caroli occaſu erubuit, ſed noſtrum &amp; in Occidente Solem Venerabatur.</p>
            <p>Cum vero Platonicè nobiſcum ageretur, Aurea<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> laſſato ferro Soecula redirent, &amp; in priſtinum omnia ſtatum re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dintegrarentur; Cui ille loco, quibus honoribus ſucceſſit, Vos appello judices: Noſtis enim quam aequis mentis pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deribus, quantis animi libramentis, dubia trutinaverat; quantos legis nodos judicij acumine loevigavit; quamque in diſtribuendâ juſtitiâ caecè erat oculatus. Et quoniam Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipibus viris placuiſſe inter laudes ultimas nunquam cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſebatur, Illuſtriſſimo <hi>Ormoniae</hi> Duci erat Charus, cujus una approbatio aliquem vel inveniret vel faceret inſignem,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:59733:26"/>
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nuſq, cujus calculus totam famoe urnam impleret, nigra<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> omnia quam foeliciſſime dealbaret, Habet enim id digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tati proerogativum <hi>Euſtacius,</hi> ut Invidioſus ſit; ipſa quip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe Majeſtas quamvis venustiſſima, ſplenijs decoratur, &amp; nihil plebi niſi quod plebeium, omni ex parte placiturum eſt.</p>
            <p>Ille, &amp; in aetatis ſuae, &amp; Regni tempeſtatibus, tribunal aſcendit; cum enim revaleſcit intemperies attentiore curâ &amp; majore arte opus eſt ne recrudeſcant vulnera, quam Solertiam ille mirificè praeſtitit, &amp; inter ſuos morbos Rei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publicae ſaluti totus incubuit, quam vigil in obeundis ſuis erat munijs, &amp; jam conſtat, adhuc enim Illius vivit in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtria, Ejuſ<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> labores catenati diſſolutum ferè Regni hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jus ſtatum etiamnum ligant, &amp; amico componunt Ordine:</p>
            <p>Quod<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> civilibus non magis quam Eccleſiaſticis rebus erat intentus, vel inde colligimus, ex opulentiſſimis quibus Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiam reditibus auxit, qui tam prodigè extiterunt largi ut aliqui multo minore pretio inter alios emiſſe caelos fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>antur, Sed <hi>quae Deo damus reddere potius quam do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nare</hi> dicimur, <hi>Mau ritius</hi> tamen ſummâ laude dignus est quod debita perſolverit: Nihil enim vel in Religione vel in honeſtate Supererogatorium eſt, Nec majorem quis glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riam poteſt conſequi quam ut verè honeſtus diceretur. Noluit <hi>Euſtacius</hi> ut haeredes ulli Chriſti patrimonium de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coquerent, ut Regis inſtar Babylonici ſacra Templi Vaſa inebriarent, aut Coronatas Sanctuarij patinas vel Baccho, vel litarent Cereri.</p>
            <p>Et inter alias ejus munificentias, Nos etiam particulam habemus; ne enim Orientis literae ſub frigidiore hoc Coelo langueſcerent, Hebraico Praelectori Stipendium deſtinavit, &amp; hoc certe in dono de bonis omnibus meretur: Haec vera eſt magnificentia, non viros ſed Artes ditare, &amp; in Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premis
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:59733:26"/>Doctrinam tabulis haeredem conſcribere; At eheu pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rierunt omnes qui talia meditabantur beneficia. <hi>Nulli niſi morituri Scientiis ſunt munifici,</hi> &amp; profectò par eſt ut tam nobile Heroici Spiritus ſpecimen à talibus ſolum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modo exhiberetur, ab eis Scilicet vel qui caelos intraturi ſunt, vel qui jam intraverant, immortales enim fovere Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entias, vere Angelicum est; Huic vel illi viro aliqui for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſſe ſunt benigni, ſuaeque non minus ambitioni quam clienti inſerviunt, ſed ſint munifici, &amp; cum prodigere ſtatutum ſit; Cur non Diogeni aeque ac Cinnamo dare ſumma habe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retur nobilitas; at quis cum <hi>Euſtacio</hi> artes intereà obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turus eſt? Quis praelectiones aedificat? in quibus faeliciùs multo doctiùſ<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> quam in lapidibus Spiraret; <hi>O beatas &amp; generoſas verè, Margaretae &amp; Savilli animas! quae in duobus Profeſſoribus bina Aeternitati Collegia erexe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sed ad Cancellarium redimus, &amp; magni illius Viri fata dolemus ſimul &amp; congratulamur: mori enim non tam triſte ſonat ac timores noſtri metus<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> nobis effingunt; ſed idem ferè eſt, ac de Hebraicis Cancellarij donis latinè loqui; <hi>Transferuntur</hi> nempe pij, &amp; quanquam Omnes ad inſtar Moſis inter obeundum non evaneſcant, Eandem tamen metam repetunt; at <hi>Euſtacio</hi> noſtro (Verbis parcite) haud abſimilis contigiſſe mors videtur, ejus enim inter has Solennitates Corpus nullibi apparet, nec <hi>Mauritium</hi> hodier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no die ſed Sarcophagum ejus ſumus ſepulturi, &amp; praeſentes hi Exequiarum ritus quam Exactiſſima morientium bono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ſunt Emblemata; Non enim viros, ſed lodices, non <hi>Mauritios,</hi> ſed ſarcophaga tumulamus: Quid enim aliud corpus eſt, quam theca animae; quae cum Sacris pectoribus inſederit, <hi>Corpus, Aegiſue</hi> appellatur, cum vero detrahi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, aut loricae, aut cadaveris, aut abjecto cophini nomine eſt contentum. Omnia <hi>bonorum</hi> ſunt immortalia; nihilque
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:59733:27"/>praeter Terminum, Mors eſt: Eſt ſecunda inter Chriſtianos notio, vel ſi mavultis, eſt umbra Idaearum intùs divinitate quâdam conceptarum, Caeleſtia contemplantibus gaudia, quae tamen exprimere non valent, niſi Chimaerae hujus non tam ope quam Miniſterio utantur: Beatitudinis quippe ſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia, aequè ac <hi>caeterae,</hi> ſua cudit verba, rebus apta magis quam Elegantia, &amp; talia inter pios <hi>mori</hi> &amp; <hi>Sepeliri</hi> ſunt. Eis omnibus idem iter eſt, eadem<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> calcanda eſt via, licèt alter pedes, Equeſque fortaſſe caelos aſcendit alter, vel cum Elia in quadriga illùc flammea peregrinatur, eaſdem alij febris praeſtat vices. Ille quem amiſſum noſtra deflet igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantia ab Angelorum choris excipitur, inter<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> Supinos illos extaſiarum plauſus nostrae jam ridentur lachrimae: Sed requieſcant pij Cineres, &amp; mortalitatis taedium edormiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant, diſcant<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> a <hi>Mauricio</hi> poſteri. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t ſi vel famae, vel immortalitati conſulant, &amp; bene Vivant, &amp; Minerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia elargiantur, laudabilique &amp; ingenuâ hâc ambitione ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti, terrâ<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> coeloque ſunt futuri Nobiles.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>JO. JONES</hi> In Art. Mag. Sacrae &amp; individuae Trinitatis Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legij juxta Dublin Soc. Comit. De Arran Sacel. Domeſt.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
